I love Joan hi this is Joanne Bordeaux
Joan is a very very good friend of mine
in fact she's a very good friend of a
lot of people a lot of people
experienced her as a as beyond a good
friend and I've known you I mean I think
I've officially known you since I think
probably around 2000 since like 2000 or
so right and at first i I knew of you or
I knew I knew you as people knew you in
general um through and we'll be getting
into this but at the time you were a
leader at at landmark which is a
transformational company that I'm sure
we're gonna go deep into this struggle
was started by Warner Earhart and I had
been we had just started circling and we
were doing these things called the art a
experience which is we're circling it's
you know got most of its early
development in and you had connected
apparently each other story that a lot
of the people that took your courses
came in did ours and then ended up
staying in ours right and and you were
became you were really good friends with
a lot of a lot of the students and I
knew you just basically on the periphery
yes when I really got to know you I
would say when I really met you was the
person I started circling with Gerry
Candelaria the two of you had started
dating and Gerry died a couple years ago
and you were dating him at the time and
I was starting to I was trying to like
get to know you more at that time but I
wouldn't say I really really knew you
and then we died I kind of had a sense
when I when I looked at you I was like I
and I knew I knew who Gerry was and I
knew I knew the kinds of things that be
come possible when you meet Jerry and I
couldn't even imagine what it must have
been like for you and so I asked you and
I know that Jerry I would imagine that
first it was had a lot to do with just
knowing Jerry would want that would want
me to do that right yeah but but I mean
within seconds but it just what it went
beyond you know
scary's friendship right yeah in very
good friends over a very intense period
of your life I mean these things came
into question for you like so many so
many deep foundational I remember
conversations that we had as you were
processing the sure the Jerry phenomena
that had to hit you and everything
connected with that and of course yeah
that's and very wedded to a lot of that
that that ground or where that comes
from and so I and I just kind of in a
certain sense I just had this I remember
in my heart I just had this instinct to
just swoop you up and make sure you're
okay and and of course what I ended up
finding out is like I ended up in a
whole world there's a whole world to you
and now you're so nestled into my into
my world there's my world and then
there's Joan and they're kind of like
they're very similar worlds at this
point yeah so I think to you and and
having you as my friend and and getting
the opportunity just to share you like
this I am so grateful for our
relationship I'm so grateful for our
friendship it's very basic and
foundational for me yeah you know you're
my go-to person right what I can't quite
make sense of my reality mm-hmm
there's a couple of people I go to one
is my spouse well I've been with folks
million years 47 years mm-hmm and the
other person is you and when the problem
is with my spouse I definitely go to you
return yes totally you know you have
such a you have such a colorful life I
think the but the most present thing
that's going on is II just started
basically writing about sex and a new
magazine tell me a little bit about this
a little bit about this this what you're
writing about what this last article
what the context of it was what your and
you're currently writing the current one
that's gonna go in the next edition or
something right yeah it's this new
platform and it's a platform that
currently consists of an online magazine
which is gorgeous and my it's my friend
Audrey's and she asked if I'd write for
her and I said I'd love doing the right
spin you what do you want me to write
about and she said sex and I thought
great that would be great
and so the first article I wrote is
about sex and aging because I think that
area has this very bad rap right and I
think I
think people who are looking toward
getting old like maybe your start
looking toward getting old when you're
in your 40s yes like before that
especially for me I didn't really think
that was possible
other people got old yeah and so I think
when people are looking at age thing
they think they're gonna have to limit
or forego their sexual expression their
sexual behavior and I think that's also
kind of institutionalized in certain
cultures where it's understood your
forego that like at least in India as
India used to be you know you were a
householder but then you'd let that go
and you know become a like spiritual
student right so it's like something
that you had or did give it by a certain
age or context and then there was
something that you could let go of and
get rid of or we're supposed to get rid
of or not your Wild Oats and then move
on to more important things of course in
other cultures like the French culture
that's it isn't that way at all but I
think in the u.s. in particular there's
a enormous puritanical streak that runs
through American not American but US
culture right right and it's
it's exacerbated by a whole bunch of
cliches about aging and sexuality
there's the cliche about the dirty old
man and there's the cliche about the
horny old woman and they're both like
like disgusting caricatures yeah and
you're afraid that you'll end up that
way right it's it's an area I think
where there's not much critical thinking
yeah and so I like that area and I think
I think sexual expression just gets
better gets better for me yeah I don't
know that it's that's ubiquitous and it
gets better for everyone but I think the
the part of sex that's biological as you
age there certainly things that are
issues biological issues you can do a
whole bunch of stuff about those issues
what goes on question to a great degree
is the ontological psychological stuff
yeah yeah totally well well just
something that you just I think posited
right and in the background about it
right which was you took it out of
something that you have in a certain age
to something that you could express
better is the word that you said as you
got older yes and that that that's
probably not that well in fact
observational II that's not the common
view or understanding of sex but what
you're saying is that and you even made
a distinction from the biological right
in fact he said the biological is kind
of the the stuff you can do stuff
specifically about dress yeah but that's
not that's yeah that's not
I think that's not the piece that
damages people's futures it's all of the
imagining that you somehow deteriorate
like psyche like like your capacity for
it deteriorates and I don't I'm 76 so
I'm gonna buy that I better buy it soon
right yes
what what they say is biologically it'll
have much more time to buy it right you
probably you know you're about halfway
there I'd say yeah but so so right there
there's I think what you're talking
about is that there's what I heard you
say basically is that there you're the
people have an amount one people have
futures right and that they're imagined
and that's an assumed cultural imagined
future yes an almost certain kind of
future cause that's almost certain you
have less sex right the sex goes away
like it you wither away in fact there's
something about like if you were to do
that when you're older that's there's
something disgusting about that or
something yeah something disgusting
maybe your development is arrested in
certain ways if you're interested in
that yeah pack a pack of agreed-upon
lies so you're just not like so what
like a couple things is like one of the
things that I would imagine what I'm
hearing is that what you're writing
about in in the magazine is and you and
this is this is some writing you're
gonna be doing ongoing like like if
there's a commitment that you have to
write or I do cuz it's fun yeah
if it's starting yes you're not going to
do it fact in fact I often joke I'm like
seems like retirements working out good
for you this is an example right yes
somebody say yes yeah absolutely
so that so this thing about so one of
the things that your experience flies in
the face of Reni is a there's a whole
cultural narrative about that and so
yeah tell me tell us a little bit about
your experience what is your experience
is it 76 year old woman I mean I know
that you've been on a ride right what's
what's some of the ride that you've been
on like what is your experience now as a
76 years well one thing is so older I
get the more stay I feel I have also the
older I get the more say you feel you
say yeah I feel I have about how I am
gonna respond to various stimuli in my
life so let me see what I want to draw
out about that the older I get the less
of a victim I am to my circumstances and
the less irresponsible I am and by by
responsible I mean actually taking on
inventing for myself that I am cause in
the matter of my life while I'm not
necessarily cause in the matter of my
situations that I'm in I am causing the
matter of how I react respond to them so
so that makes everything better
and that makes everything easier that
makes everything more peaceful and and
one of the things that makes better is
sex like if I'm turning myself off I'm
clear no one else is turning me off
nobody else is doing that to me that's
that's on me and it's it's fine it's a
possible way to be as turned off
conversely being turned on and hot
that's on me too and I can do that if I
want I have say over my sexuality it
doesn't mean that I'm turned on all the
time but I have say and I couldn't be
and this is coming from someone who is
really good at blaming other people in
situations for why things are why the
fuck they are so yeah it's yeah it's a
good yes so this is it this is a
turnaround from from a place that you
came from at one point right so this
this the sense of just what you're
saying it goes back actually to what you
just said about aging right there's a
situation called aging right that has
certain biological things that go on and
you could make and there's a situation
called aging yeah like at that code yet
they're working on it but yeah but then
there's your response to what what's
happening and what you're making what I
heard you say is that you're not coming
from the place well I I understand that
you trained yourself to not come from
the place practice not coming from the
place a lot of practice right yeah age
for you isn't you're not a victim to
being 76 right yeah it's like well I do
notice
people have a reaction to that like I
think when I was in my 60s a lot of
times I just I didn't lie about my age
but it was like a sin of omission right
I just didn't talk about it and I let
people assume whatever they were gonna
assume about how old I was because I cuz
I felt as soon as I said how old I am
then people are captive of certain
pictures and images and like they
stopped relating to what's fair right
now and fill in all the blanks with
bullshit yeah yeah totally and so you so
you haven't really been one to announce
your age well I mean I think what I did
one I was became 69 or 70
uh-huh because I saw that there was a
certain percentage of people usually
women yeah almost entirely women may be
entirely women who saw some future for
themselves in that yeah and I like
providing that I like people having more
freedom and more possibility and more
joy and more happiness you know what
other than yeah yeah well I think right
there
I mean I'm this one of the things I've
always appreciated about you and I just
heard it and just what you just said
right which is you've been trapped
you're true you're actually tracking and
responding to a whole culture like I
like people knowing that they can be
basically you're you break a lot of
bolts and so like there was a point
where you didn't talk about your age
because there was all kinds of baggage
that people put you in but then you got
to a certain age where it's like you
were really clear that there were all
kind
of Constraints about this age right yeah
and so you're not living in them right
you're not you're not like you're not
just swallowing them like you know like
I can screw myself in the zoom now and I
like I could see these lines and
beautiful things I think yes yeah
ways that what is that part of it like
for you um so I've traded on that for
you know probably my entire life like
how I look so should be traded on the
traded yeah like homeless actually
there's a little time when I was so
embedded in being a hippie that I didn't
like I gave but then I did again so I
have attachments in that area like I
think I'll have brown hair till I die
I think I'm never going to do the going
gray oh my god you know you make your
choices in life well you know I think
the thing about the thing about you Joan
is that there's there's not too many
people that I encounter that know you
that don't have the I don't hear the
word word hot about you come to mind
something very hot about you right and
and that like the there's something in
in what's hot about you right it's
interesting because as you get older
right hotness is still shining shining
through you it's not it's like ladies
that I know that's that's a good
question I like that I like being the
recipient of things like that but I'm
not like after that yeah it's not like I
don't wake up and think oh how much be
hot today no yes well what is that yeah
yeah well what do you think it is I
would imagine as something to do with
whatever it is that notices it and ask
that question I think it has something
to do with authenticity yeah yeah yeah I
think so
you know and what in for you there's a I
know there's a deep so there's what do
you actually what do you mean by
authenticity I think a capacity that can
be developed where you like call
yourself on your shit right right I
think that's the main piece it's
and then and for me in the calling
myself on shit I mean and I don't think
I ever do it immediately but I'm pretty
much town honorable for at some point
being in so much pain that although Oh
God alright I'm gonna just say it I'm
just gonna say how it is for me yeah and
in in that I can see if there's things I
want to do about it
like you know like having so much
attention on myself like so I really I
really want to pay so much attention to
myself
that's the expense of other people I
don't think so and then I can do
something about it that I can't until I
and when it's a big secret
yeah and I'm a bad terrible person for
being obsessed right totally so there's
a there's a there's a part of it which
is being authentic when I'm hearing a
big part of it is is this willingness
that you have part of authenticity is
calling yourself on is it fair to say
all of your inauthenticities yeah you
can absolutely say that and the other
thing is it's never fun oh good here's
an opportunity point to this in
authenticity no it always looks like
don't do that they won't like you they
won't accept you they'll know what a bad
person you jerk you are and then they'll
kick you out of the club whatever the
club is yeah yeah so for example yeah
I'm about to in the middle of writing
the second article for the magazines and
it's about but it takes face of me is
like in my late teens early 20s and I've
discovered sex as a commodity like like
a power like a superpower like I
discover I could even have sex with JFK
you know if you if you are strategic
enough and you're a woman mm-hmm
and you've kind of learned some sexual
tricks you could have sex with anyone
and thereby given given the culture now
given women don't have much power in the
60s that is a pathway to having some
power right and and for me that was
dangerous there's something dangerous
about writing about that because I do
not consider myself a victim of that I
consider lived inside of a particular
paradigm there were constraints and
limitations like they're always are
inside of any context or paradigm and I
figured out how to get some power it's
it's I think a kind of unpopular thing
to say now on the other hand it really
describes something that was very true
for me then and you know will I be
kicked out of the club the club like the
me to club yeah yeah totally
I really get into writing about that
story and what what the the the sense of
risk right which is so what I'm hearing
actually is that you this is authentic
we talked about we're starting to talk
what is it that makes you hot because
you don't wake up in the morning and
have this imperative like I'm gonna be
hot and put your makeup on just uh but
there's something that shines through
right that yeah that even it even like
in you and all the things that you know
they're saying about aging there's
something about it that like shines its
it shines they're just it animates it in
some way for me and I think for a lot of
people and just to see some contexts
that for a lot of people you have you
have led courses for years and landmark
and in different kinds of different
kinds of things and all their spiritual
organizations and stuff like that
and we'll talk we can we could probably
talk about a lot of that history but the
what I'm kind of getting is that when we
asked what was it about what is that
never really asked that question about
hotness before um but there is something
worried and then you said well I think
it has something to do with I call
myself out on my shit right I I you can
count on me pretty much to notice where
I'm like inauthentic basically and you
care about it or you talk about it in
fact you do in fact it's the last thing
that you want to do great yeah and then
but then you do it yeah great and then
something happens out of that yeah and
one of the places that you're noticing
that you may be doing that now is when
you someone came to you and asked you to
write about sex at 76 years old what you
find yourself writing about right is a
way in which for you as a woman at that
time a way to get power right you found
out was through sex and one of the
things that you notice that's scary
about this and it may be like points to
the authenticity the act of authenticity
is it you're risking something and I
think what I heard you say is that
there's something about that you don't
see yourself as a victim in that
right that you sense is speaking into
something that could have some blowback
or yeah like oh you're in denial
cuz it was really bad at that time and
yeah there were there were limitations
mm-hmm
there were and and I like it better now
but yeah yeah totally
oh what what is it that I mean how did
you go about learning that like what was
the ride like well I personally where
did you grow you grew up in New York
right yeah middle class would be mobile
Jewish family and when I was 10 we moved
to a very upwardly mobile part of Long
Island called the five towns and yeah
that's I was I never considered myself a
Jewish princess but I probably was I had
friends who I definitely would consider
as Jewish princess is here because they
were richer than my family right right
just so I know because I'm not that
familiar with Jewish princesses like I
know that I've obviously heard the name
but what's a Jewish princess basically
supposed to be like spoiled rotten
okay okay got it uh-huh yeah and you had
a sister - right an older sister four
years older yeah yeah and there was some
there was some kind of dynamic as there
are in all family well I she was
I wanted to be okay because she you know
as a young child she could do things I
couldn't do and and I wanted to be her
and I she was an artist and I wanted to
be an artist but she was such a good
artist I knew I could never be an artist
so there was a lot of my identity I
defined by virtue of not being my sister
right right okay got it but eventually
she ended up in the camp with my parents
and I ended up on the other side of that
cultural gap that which was called the
generation gap which wasn't so much it
was generational but it was more where
your head was yeah yeah I'm your exact
age so like Ramdas who was a few years
older than me when he was definitely on
the side of the gap that always on
that's the side of the gap yes you know
a bunch of years older than me but
definitely right definitely right
totally okay got you so it's so you were
your friends and it sounds like your
sister right we're on one side of the
camp yep and then you ended up on the
other side of the camp on the other side
right which sounds like sounds like well
the sixties it was the sixties yeah and
so how did you when you were did you
stay at home until you were like 18 and
then you go to college I went to college
when I was 17 when you're 17 okay got it
I was really young for my grade and I
went to college when I was 17 but found
it was not to my liking I went to
Emerson College in Boston and I wanted
to be an actress and I
was I don't think I knew that part yes I
wanted to be an actress and I was
excluded from getting certain parts
because I had a really really thick not
just New York accent I had a really
thick Long Island accent which to me is
the most when people think of New York
accents they are really talking about
Long Island accent rate right and and
then I fell in love with this guy from
who was had just graduated college and
he was moving to New York and I thought
I don't want to be here anymore not
getting parts and you know I want to go
there and be with him so I came back
home to my parents house they were very
much against me quit in college and I
started living at home again which is
just miserable and he broke up with me
like like almost immediately which was
devastating because that was my way out
right and and then I started hanging out
in Manhattan I started working in the
city and hanging out and smoking at
Spartan taking amphetamine I discovered
amphetamine that's like wow had you had
you been introduced to psychedelics by
that time no not yet okay that happened
when I was 20 I took LSD right for the
first time yes got you and that was in
New York yeah uh-huh
I said so you're in New York yeah and he
started like you're smoking pot and you
discovered and said it means yes and
then how did you make your way through
New York what happened
different things happened so that thing
about well one thing that happened
before that was I my home life in terms
of sexuality was super suppressive right
and you know my mother would say things
my mother was like very loving really
great but she would say things like
don't embarrass me by getting a bad
reputation reputation and some
households maybe that would have meant
getting bad grades yeah yes my house
that man having having sexual
intercourse yeah that's what that meant
that reputation equal screwing right
right so I was very so you were being
watched and you had like a ton of
pressure from your parents and their
image on the line connected to your
sexuality yeah yeah like like I thought
oh if I if I have sex I'm hurting my
mother right right clean that that's
weird isn't it Wow except I really
wanted to have sex I mean I was like you
wanted to hurt your mother
careful I'm a bad person yes I really
wanted to so my excuse eventually having
it I think was the Cuban Missile Crisis
[Applause]
yes
arms to Cuba and Kennedy took a stand
and everyone was talking this could be
it this could be it I thought holy shit
this could be it I'm not gonna die
virgin right and besides I'm not gonna
have
future then I can have sex without
hurting my mother because none of us are
gonna have a future that's when I first
had sex is 17 well I just want to get I
just want to kind of just sink into that
for a second that's just it's that one
is crawl inside of that because it's
like if I have well I'm imagining there
was a there was a way where if it's like
most families right there's the there's
the explicit right there's a way that
where that was explicit right like don't
your mother's saying don't ruin my met
with my reputation so there's that
explicit but I would imagine is also the
implicit structure an atmosphere that
you just knew that you should probably
didn't even need to say it I would
imagine yeah that she said it only made
it explicit because you know like people
like Marilyn Monroe
we're considered like sexy and hot and
whores
mm-hm yeah why she was considered a
whore yeah so being sexy and hard yeah I
think it's almost it's interesting I I
want to slow down on that for for a
second because I it's it's interesting I
don't it happened to I discovered the
analytics for videos there's a whole
button that you press and there's like
analytics that show you could show you
that the graph of the age range of the
people that watch you and all this stuff
it's long and I just discovered that the
age range of most of my viewers are I
think between the age of 25 and 35 I
think right now yeah so I'm just
imagining you know you know it's funny
I'm getting to the age where I'm
noticing differences in sensibilities of
generations and I just heard a woman
talk and just hit
just younger woman just probably like
early 20s talk about friends with
benefits like but with without changing
a beat great conversation and and I was
like that you like when I was really
young you would never hear a woman say
that right yes like without it at least
being a thing that she was saying right
like making her a certain kind of person
yeah no it just makes her a part of the
mainstream yeah absolutely so it's like
really really what's possible but the
sensibility around relationships and
around sexuality especially with women
has very much changed so this change but
but I would say you know very much
change by virtue of things like feminism
yeah yeah yeah and probably psychedelics
cuz I think everything is very much
changed by virtue of you know wider
spread use of psychedelics yeah yeah
which is which is something I want to
dive into with you a bit and your
experience of that but there's but just
that sense I just want to kind of crawl
inside of that because I don't think I
would imagine like a lot of people
really maybe don't even it would have a
hard time even comprehend seing this but
like literally as a woman as you at that
time in your life right because it just
wasn't in your family that was in the
culture to you're just coming out of the
50s right where the Norman Rockwell
painting and appropriateness it was so
oppressive right yes such that it just
became implicit and self-evident that if
you have sex you could disgrace your
entire lineage yes right yes so like
there's this there's your biology and
all of your biological impulses that are
natural and to procreate and all the
different things and then there's a
narrative and a pressure connected to
your identity and all the things that
formed your identity today you could if
you went with your biology if you did
what you wanted or even though it was in
your heart you your whole family was on
the line yes that is quite that is quite
a predicament yeah and it's some well
it's so anti evolution isn't it yeah
it's such an anti evolutionary impulse
or culture it's yeah
right right totally so that's so
basically it became okay for you to have
sex once you it looked like there was an
almost certain guarantee you could have
sex without the consequences of ruining
your family because there was a future
that called everyone's family would be
gone there would be no you're free to
have sex exactly
that's amazing Wow
and in once and so you had sex yes yes
well well that but then but then you've
been having I mean I didn't I didn't
know the mechanics of it the guy had sex
with you know Oh was like eighteen and
yeah it wasn't fun but I was glad it was
over with great great and then I saw two
Pro to learn and perfect things and
learn a bunch of things great totally
and so when when when no one died and
you had a future right and I get this
sense of like so when you went to New
York that's when you you started living
opposite of the of the way that you were
raised I had started when I lived at
home in high school I mean I the first
time I smoked pot was like in the spring
of my senior year no one smoked pot you
know
it wasn't a thing jazz musicians smoke
pot yeah yeah Bohemians smoke pot nobody
you know wasn't and I I smoked it then a
little bit because he couldn't really
get it and but I was rebellious you know
I like would take the car and my friends
and I would just you know drive hundreds
of miles away and then I'd bring the car
back and my mother would take did you
take the car which of course had all the
mileage on it now and I'd say why would
you think I took your car yeah yeah why
would I do that yeah yeah totally
totally so I think the thing I'm it's
funny because I don't think we've ever
like our conversations go all over the
map so let going back to this and like
really kind of chronologically going
over your history I'm it's interesting
it gives me some insight right yeah
about things that ways you express
yourself and things that you contend
with and things you struggle with and
even the ways that you talk about being
authentic right is one of the first
things that came up for you right when
we looked at the ontology of hotness
right basically right is is it there's
this thing about authenticity which is
is sharing one of the ways that you can
be authentic is by sharing how you're
not and that there's a risk in that yeah
and so it's interesting cuz I'm I'm
feeling the culture right the
constraints you were born into it so
many internal contradictions right and
there's a side that that it was really
clear what you're supposed to do and
supposed to be and your sister was it
right and
you you wanted to be like your sister so
you wanted to be the sense of the ideal
right or I wanted to be but at one point
I thought I just said fuck it because
it's not happening
yeah that's not going to happen so then
I became the Antichrist right so just
there right like so so so your dreams
your dreams were a dream of like a
because when I try to imagine you being
that it just hurts right the idea of you
kind of like taking on and being
whatever a princess is and being my
imagination of what all that is I just I
just I just can't I don't think I can't
see it it just something inside goes
that would just be so wrong yeah
however there was a way in which you're
you're like you're dreaming motivational
systems were oriented towards that
that's what was the ideal yeah and then
of course right you're you but this but
this didn't have anything to do with you
yes and so you end up as you as you grow
up and as this becomes more this and you
become more you and you realize that
you're not that then you have to do this
other move right which is become not
that like yes I am that I am not that so
you became defined by that yeah
absolutely
she can't be the not unless you bring
along yeah but that right totally so
that's it it's interesting cuz I think
what that's what a lot of people call
authenticity it seems to be this is more
yeah yeah yeah I hate that when people
call that authentic right on the street
that's what passes for authenticity yeah
yeah which is I think some of the things
about like a lot of that stuff has to
with victimhood I believe yeah right
right which is like that's bad and I'm
good yeah it's that but of course you're
so dependent on another yeah right yeah
so one of the ways that I'm just kidding
of like what a freedom you must have
found in copping to that whole thing
going on inside of you right of like oh
yeah being honest about what I actually
think right is like I actually just hate
you because you're a good person and but
I want to be a good person in a lake
therefore I just want to hide my face
and impress you or something and you say
it right you say it and like there's
something that releases in that that
just seems existentially awakening or
something like that something that
really didn't happen no to my early 50s
yeah okay so though the roles I was in
seem to smack of authenticity yes and
while because I was a writer I would
there were times when I would be able to
[Music]
expose that in my writing but in my
everyday on the court as the life rate
that was hidden right okay got it so so
thats so writing that's been a big part
of your life in fact it's just recently
come back after 30 years 40 years
yeah so you so you went to college you
wanted to be you wanted to be an actor
yes
rad actress then you came back lived
back at home and escaped in New York
yeah had sex had a ton of sex yeah a ton
of sex right a tenant's X which was also
it sounds like was an introduction to a
whole culture
yeah yeah you're right like the
introduction it was that is that was
that your first beat into spirituality
in the 60s that world was that New York
or was that after New York or know that
it was in in New York I was about 22
okay
23 I read the autobiography of a yogi' I
had already taken Ella stage okay and
then I yeah autobiography of a yogi'
yeah
so you took LSD in your early 20s yeah
it was that a pivotal was that like you
were kidding like totally huh cuz it
opened up worlds that I never knew I
mean sound so cliched never knew existed
but it did yeah yeah well do you do you
remember much about the experience that
you had was it or was it mostly like was
it so much about the audience wasn't
like a an experience like unity with the
cosmos that came later
I could see people's complicity yeah I
could just see oh they're saying one
thing but there being something else
right what is it was like a super it was
like having a superpower like oh like
what apparently on the surface isn't
what's going on here at all
Wow so it's interesting because I just
got this sense of on some level up until
that point you like your life was kind
of almost of and working out that
tension yeah being defined by that
tension right yeah
but I thought that I took it all
personally yeah defined by the attention
like this is just me yeah this isn't
physic isn't a human experience this is
just personal right totally and so
something about when you took acid or
LSD that background became foreground
yeah
and you could almost like yeah I get
this sense of like seeing the matrix of
it yes yeah that seems like a
game-changer yeah was completely yeah
that's a that is a game-changer it's
also I mean if you think about it like
with you know Allah I mean a lot of
people write about this the one that I
know of that initially wrote about this
in a psychological it was Piaget where
he talked about development right was is
that you is that you see with the level
of development that you're at you don't
see it and then at a certain point the
level that you're at starts to is you
start to grow in it or it becomes more
complicated and you start to have all
these dichotomies and that if if things
go well it's not given that it'll go
like this but if things go well in some
way there's a certain point where you
pop out in the level that you were
seeing with becomes the level that you
were see and you're now at a higher
level of complexity and the level is is
about kind of you could say you know
integrating that level into this new
level of complexity until another level
that happens again so I really got the
sense of of yeah you were in all of that
you were you had all those
contradictions and all those inoffensive
cities and we're in response to it in
your family right and in yourself and so
so you've been your of it I would
imagine your fears and your self-talk
and all of the things were we're trying
on some level to work that out but
embedded in it and so LSD had this
experience of where you could see
the matrix of it yeah Wow Wow
and so then you open your eyes and you
looked around and you're now in the in
this situationally you're in the same
world but not but you're in a very
different world
yeah and is that when you started to
write
I have always written I had always
written that was my fallback if I
couldn't be an actress that was I mean
the actress thing I think the writing
thing was like oh wait is the very basic
mode of self-expression for me but the
actress thing was all about being famous
right
yeah Oh interesting yeah it wasn't like
a mode of self-expression
yeah but writing was but writing was
yeah yeah
in fact you even talked to a little bit
about ago about that there was uh yeah
you were starting to push the edges with
your writing like you could say stuff in
your writing that were really true
inauthentic but then your interactions
in the world it's not like you were that
person in the world
in your experience right yeah no I
wasn't that person yeah because I know
that you have written how many books
have you written actually eight but you
know and they were
all nonfiction and a lot of how-to stuff
so how I ended up writing my first book
was I worked for a small publishing
company in Manhattan and my boss was the
president and I was his assistant and I
was discovering yoga at the same time
and I had become a vegetarian and this
is like around what year 64 maybe early
early mid sixties yeah yeah and and I a
couple of times I invited him over I had
a loft I invited him over and I made him
vegetarian food and then he quit the
publishing company and became a literary
agent and he asked me if I wanted to
write a vegetarian cookbook and you know
he thought that that was a really great
idea and he coached me on how to write a
proposal and he sold the book to holt
rinehart and Winston which is a major
big major publishing company here and
they gave me $2,000 which is to me at
the time like two million dollars yeah
yeah yeah and and I wrote this cookbook
called victory through vegetables of
course he did vegetables and it became
very very popular yeah and it went to
paperback and then small paperback and
the rights were sold to several
countries and it was excerpted in some
magaz
and then quite surprisingly publishing
companies would come to my agent and my
ex-boss and say well what is my name at
the time was Jones we know because I was
married it's them to Richie Lina
Joan Wiener wanna write no because I was
a hippie and and that was a thing better
yes mm-hmm
and and I would make up what I wanted to
write about and then somebody would buy
it and that happened for a long time Wow
Wow
so the books that I wrote in that time
that were not like victory through
vegetables or the Illustrated
hassle-free make your own clothes book
or the biography of Swami Satchidananda
well a book called a motherhood book
which event was about my experience of
pregnancy and early motherhood and then
I wrote a book called the ultimate loss
which is about what happens for parents
when a child dies and they were the most
literary oh so so so that when you
because I know at some point you well
did you write that autobiography for for
the yogi yeah so when did you and you
became part of that whole well I was
sitting with him - what was the integral
yoga Institute on West End Avenue in
Manhattan right and who met him he was
he was a mass
yeah yeah and it was one of the first
wave of teachers who came to the US in
the 60s silly
he came Suzuki Roshi started the Zen
Center in San Francisco was here Yogi
Bhajan who was a Sikh teacher was here a
Swami Bhaktivedanta who started the Hari
Krishna thing was here you know they're
all here and they're all kind of hanging
out together I mean there were times
when they'd actually hang out together
and I met Swami Satchidananda very soon
after he had come to the US and he asked
me if I would be his secretary and I
said yeah and I you know moved in to the
integral yoga Institute which is a big
big apartment and I told my husband I
was doing that and I said you can come
or not and he would sometimes be there
but he had a head shop in lower Eastside
called the electric Lotus just so I know
what how is your mom narrating your life
at this point if they knew about it but
they need certain things there were
things they couldn't escape knowing
right she was like her narrative well
you know Joan Joan is just different
mm-hmm right right okay got it
okay and by then I had a yogi named I've
received a cheetah
Sita Gita Wow Wow
so what was it like so tell me a little
bit about how did you get from so here
you are in the early mid sixties right
this is this is I mean you're talking
about stuff that's like changed culture
right you're talking about people and
things that when people talk about this
they talk about like this being the
beginning of a whole new wave of
consciousness the whole yes essentially
so you're in New York at that time and
find yourself in the middle of all that
but not only in the middle of all that
you find yourself with one of the
prophets of it yeah he was if you see
the movie of Woodstock he was the Swami
who opens up the Woodstock Festival of
course you were his secretary Wow Wow
I mean that I believe in just that's a
symbol
I mean Woodstock is symbol of the whole
of that whole thing then on some level
threw down a stream of in ways that I'm
sure that I'm I'm I will continue to
understand of my life is downstream uh
right so you so how did how did it go
from how did it how did you like what
did you start practicing yoga with him
were you a student and then he was I had
like I said I read autobiography of a
yogi' so that kind of gave me a little
tiny pinpoint view into that world yeah
then my friend Kathy who was a model had
met him and she said oh you must come
meet my swarming right so I went with
her and he gave a talk and I thought he
is talking about these realizations I
had on acid like articulating a whirl
that's very congruent with that and I'd
never met anybody like that I need smart
people and had a bunch to say but he was
an embodiment of a whole other other
level of consciousness totally and so I
just recognize that say that again you
recognize that oh absolutely and you
know he was I met him and he hugs me I
went up to him at the end of his talk
and he hugged me and he I could tell
that he loved me and liked that he loved
me and he accepted me and so that was
like a big deal for me
and so yes I was interested in yoga but
I was much more interested in him loving
me yeah yeah okay God that connection
that heart connection that like
recognition oh this person who I've
never met before loves me just because
I'm here yeah and that was the thing
that was the difference that made the
difference according to your heart yeah
was it was it was all about my heart and
our heart connection totally no that
makes a lot of sense to me knowing you
it just does like I and I think well how
it makes sense to me is well one is it's
interesting you are you know you I think
you've described yourself as a general
right you also describe yourself as a
classical Taurus you're a bull right you
there is this quality where you make
shit happen and you make shit happen at
levels that are are are unreasonable
right in terms of leading courses and
throwing parties and movements and
however it seems to be very connected to
it to that to this something or someone
captures your heart yes if you love me
all all make sure your life is great yes
yes and that quality of your heart is
one of the things that I think is so
interesting about you and about being
your friend is that there's because you
know if I think about a bowl and I think
about a general I don't necessarily like
think like words like love in heart
necessarily but for you it's very
connected to that there's a look there's
a deep almost vulnerable fact about you
and your heart that is uh that is so
devotional in its essence in my
experience yes I mean you are so right
on because if I look at what I produced
in landmark yeah I loved my manager huh
I love my manager Julie I you know she
would say look do you think you could
have a hundred more people in your
course and I would say yes cuz I loved
her and she wanted that and I love the
person who invented all the stuff in the
wisdom area Brian
I loved him because he except he thought
I was just great
he thought I was just great and yeah I'd
do anything for him right right
any like great at a level of C I'm not
I'm not getting the sense it's like
great in the sense that he gave you a
reflection of yourself that you want
I'm also getting that sense with when
you were talking about with the yogi
it's not like he hugged you and there is
like a like that he reflected something
to you that you needed it was more like
it's something else it was more like a
transmission of some like a he loved you
at the level of a being that was
unconditional like and there's something
about there's the unconditioned
unconditional in all of those examples
Swami Satchidananda well what they and
and their deep appreciation of my quirks
yeah like things other people were like
really really Joan no yes
and so it's like it's it's interesting
because I think what I'm I'm like if I
if I crawl inside of that there's a it's
it's kind of like how you are with me
where I'll tell you stuff that I think
other people would not him want to
embrace right like oh god get a grip
he's been you've had all these years of
transformation and you still or like
that mask but you think that's
interesting yeah totally yeah and it's
something about I think the one of the
things I'm just getting about what as
you're talking about it is that it's
it's not like an even unconditional love
is tricky
it's a tricky it doesn't quite say it
because it it's not
like Swami that's the the yoga guy
hugged you and it wasn't like he was
looking at you and then noticing
conditions upon which he accepted as
more like he was looking at a place that
was had no conditions and he was
unambivalent about how he felt about
that right and then and then anything
you talk about afterwards is already
inside of an unconditional 'ti so that
I'm I I just it's interesting I've never
quite got it so clearly in relationship
with you about what that must have been
like to be in the gaze of that or to be
to hugged in that way cuz
I mean up until that point everything
that you've described has been just a
like it's it's like life--all kind of
when I think about your history from
before then right it's like a hall of
mirrors there's like everything has so
much at stake and there's nothing
totally obvious of what you could do and
like impulses in the you could ruin your
family and just all these iterations of
reflections with no clear like no clear
rulebook but a lot at stake and a lot on
the line and then just knowing good just
innately like fanatically curious being
that you are which is the way that you
love is you get interested in stuff I've
noticed right so one of the way and so I
would just imagine that interest of
course you're interested in all the cool
stuff but that would compromise
everything in your life right and then
you had to go become opposite of that
and then your mom had a story about you
of like well she's just you know and so
to meet somebody that was standing in
the place that opened that you got a
taste of on LSD right and just live
there and then hugged you from there
that is a that's a profound that strikes
me as a profound kind of DNA level
experience yeah no I I mean I don't
think I would have talked about it them
like that how I go through life have
gone through life is all right well okay
was it wasn't that way yesterday but
okay this is the way it is now okay it's
not pragmatic yeah yes yes and use of
course so then you just start responding
to what's in front of you
yeah uh-huh and so that response was
becoming a secretary absolutely
and traveling with him and writing his
biography yeah which is just something
we cooked up together before that he had
said I think we should do a hatha yoga
book and so he would explain the
positions and to me and I would like
sorted out and write it down and then my
friend gita hanuman who was this
extraordinary documentary filmmaker who
was also his devotee photographed him in
all these yoga positions and it was one
of the first coffee table size books on
hatha yoga was just spectacular oh wow
oh wow
interesting interesting and then then me
and that was distinct from the the
biography yeah the bar the feel is about
a year later oh wow so like lots of
spending time with them now I lived with
him yeah you lived with them it's wrote
a book but that's a whole it's
interesting like so there's living with
people right but then there's I'm
imagining living and then writing about
who you're living with right that seems
like a whole different a whole different
level
well what we
we would it was so clunky given
technology now yeah I would interview
him I'd say so tell me what it was like
growing up in Coimbatore yes and he
would tell me and we would record it on
this portable tape recorder and then I
would transcribe it you know pushing a
button and typing and I always write so
horrible that was Marmite right right
Wow and so you and you lived with him
for how long two years two years and
then his is and then when did you get
when we were you introduced to landmark
was that after that or during that or um
I moved to California in 1970 and I gave
birth to my daughter Daisy yeah and
which is your first child right my first
child was stillborn
she was born two years before she was
born in New York and her name was Gabby
Gabby okay Gabby Gabrielle and she was
born dead oh and that was yeah what a
big deal there's trouble that was just
so unexpected yeah yeah yeah
and that was
was that so just in terms of time is
that while you were living I had moved
out into organs to I was slow being his
corresponding secretary and then someone
else took over is the person who
attended to his you know room and his
food and the travel yeah all of that and
so so right as you were moving out you
were pregnant yeah yeah and you were
married
yep yeah it was reduced daughter right
Wow and so so that what was I would
imagine like
yeah what was that like I mean what how
did you get through that time yeah yeah
just time I mean people we're so
uneducated then about how you approach
someone who's grief-stricken and lost a
child yeah yeah
you know people said a lot of stupid
shit right right and I'm in agony I bet
you were
I bet you were yeah like you're in agony
and without much of what well I would
imagine not much of a narrative to be
able to hold the amount of agony no I
mean I kept thinking I should get over
it yeah like I'd say things to myself
like well it's not like she ever lived
yeah but of course she would she lived
inside of me for nine months yeah yeah
but there was no I had no frame of
reference other than I'm in pain it just
goes on and on and on yeah and it's
something wrong with me that I'm not
over this and it's been a month right
Wow and also just had not having had
kids before so not knowing not even
knowing God would it Wow Wow
just you would try to imagine how one
pieces that together because I would
imagine you have now that you have kids
you can look back and go like well of
course this is probably at least you
could have explained it to yourself more
Yeah right but the bonding that happens
I'm imagining as a as as a woman that
goes through the pregnancy is just so I
mean it's just so well one of the things
I've noticed about about Brianne in in
our relationships
so there's there's this way where I'm
like a really philosophical and like
could you know questioning the positive
questions and all the stuff and in and
it's interesting Bri and it's just kind
of like she's like it's obvious to her
like there's a way there's a way where
there's I mean she loves the fact that I
do that right she wouldn't change me in
a heartbeat but there's a there is this
way where she could do that with me but
you could also just she could cook
dinner and somehow be as connected to
that as my going to the edge of the
cosmos right with it that there's
something so inside out biologically
obvious like life
you're so identified with life right and
I yeah we're I'm imagining as a as a man
like it's very difficult for me to even
comprehend what that would be like but
but to the degree that I can it's like
but that here's the thing about it is I
just would imagine going through all of
that right and your whole body is
oriented toward to be to have a future
of being a second womb for another
family right and so you go through all
of that and then the child dies and
there's no one that you know but you
have all of that your whole last nine
months have has been in your being has
been prepped in preparation for that
second womb and then no one's there
like I just that's intense it's so
intense I mean I even had milk which was
had nowhere to go which is just dripping
out of my breasts and I I was just set
up there having a child and then there
was just no child god wow I've never
talked to you about this
No yeah I've never talked with you about
this this is really this is a this is I
feel one I'm just loving getting to know
you more I was loved getting to know you
more but like also just appreciate I'm
just appreciating I think so so like
kind of updating my experience with you
right which is where we started you have
become friends as was right when Jerry
died right in the grief that you were
again trying to comprehend out of that
experience right which yeah but I had
you know I had you yes you were holding
me yeah I had more experience I mean I
understood that I was just going to let
whatever emotional winds blew through me
I was gonna let that be yeah yeah and I
was you know was gonna take as long as
it was gonna take and right right
totally so there was you had wisdom but
what but like when you're how old were
you when when that happened 24 you're 24
Wow well Wow and so you went through all
that grief right and you moved to
California why did you move to
California was hip
mekka yeah it to be heavy yeah you had
to go be a hippie and is that when I was
there I was a hippie but you know to be
a hippie in New York was like to be a
second class hippie yeah very Francisco
was the first class hippie oh yeah
absolutely sure right right and is that
when you is that when you encountered
landmark
yeah but four years later okay it was
asked it was s then right right and then
that was a big deal this is a big deal
what happened well I had you know I had
a lot of disdain for the s training and
people's reports about the s training
because I had lived through the real
honest-to-goodness school teacher master
right this is this American guy who
wouldn't through it abandoned his wife
and family and changed his name and yeah
and people's reports about it seemed
far-fetched but then Werner and this is
this is all this is when you move to
California this was like late 60s early
70s early 70s look I got it but the end
Werner developed a relationship with
Swami Muktananda and good friends of
mine were
lived in Piedmont and they turned their
home into his ashram and Werner was
asked ramananda if he would go to
Werner's centers and meet the people
there because he Werner wanted his staff
and participants to me Swami Muktananda
and have that as part of their
experience so Werner asked my friends if
if they wanted to do the yes training
because they were now working together
on this tour and they said yes and I
felt betrayed because we were see we
were all spiritual pedia and that was
like some Western bullshit right not
Eastern right Lhasa fee yes yes which
was where it was at Eastern philosophy
so we did the S trainee and then they
were like ah for me to do it they loved
it mm-hmm they told me I would love it I
didn't believe them I thought now they
were part of his thing but so my very
very best friend in the world through
them did it and that's what turns me
okay got it I could not bear that she
had something I didn't have yeah yeah
totally so then I did it and he was the
learner was the person who led my
training yeah and I was smitten by his
authenticity by his like Rufus fucking
compassion and the level of his
authenticity and the way he could see
right into people
and be so straight with them and at the
same time be so compassionate without
the trappings of what we consider
compassion any of it you see icky things
no he's just like like like like a sword
like yeah through people's bullshit you
know was like wow right right and that
was a game-changer that was it was a
game-changer because before I had done a
couple of things I had done this course
called an Enlightenment in intensive
which is very intense and when I did
that I had a full-blown what I would
call enlightenment experience where
everything fell away like all of my
preferences and every good and all
duality kind of completely fell away and
I lived in that state for about two
weeks where I moved through the world
without attachment to my own thoughts
and it was like I moved through the
world and I was cloaked in ecstasy Wow
but that and that happened for me again
when I did the S train really yes oh wow
yeah see you're like well that one went
really well that was pretty good yeah
yeah I'd like some more back no doubt
you know it's interesting as you're
talking it's it's so it's so interesting
because I just kind of cut kind of
caught sight of a broader timeframe you
know of in some ways cuz I've been as
you know I've been in these
conversations with with John for baekje
and various people about how people are
like he's conceptualizing it as the is
the the meaning crisis and and Jordan
Hall is talking about it as the meta
crisis of this basically place where you
know secularism cut like it takes hold
in nihilism right in where we we go from
like a basically a religiously based
Western culture to losing losing the
ground of that and that happening slowly
over to through time right and and as
you're talking I'm getting this sense of
like the response to that the the
response to the loss of that ground
right are things that you were right
inside of at the very beginning of right
the whole sixties and you were right at
the the first people on that wave of
responding to that because there was
this gap right on some level where the
institutions were these basically
Christian institutions like not maybe
explicitly but all of the values that
had come from Christianity right but yet
it was people were losing the Christian
faith so judo
Christiano Christianity yeah and this is
an overgeneralization big time and as as
people were experiencing one way you
could look at is experience people were
experiencing the loss of that
meaningfulness of the ground right you
start to look at the response to that
right and so you are on to very very
what some of the first waves of the
response to the meaning crisis to the
meta crisis and we're witnesses I was
just kind of getting a sense of that
right and here we are having a
conversation about it from inside of it
yeah this is amazing this is amazing
interesting you know we I mean we've
been going for about two hours how are
you doing I knew I said well I'm good
I'm a little hot yes son has gotten
higher yes because I can break this up I
can break this up but I'm actually kind
of getting a sense of how about if we
stop now
okay and then and then let's just do
another one
yeah this is fun this is a lot of fun
it's it's what I love about it is it's
giving meaning it it gives a lot of
meaning to to the narrative you know I
mean narrative itself is meaning right
but this gives some meta meaning yes to
the unfoldment of my life so it's so
much fun for me because all I'll have to
do is is tell my version of the truth
and it happens to be that your version
of the truth touches on so many so many
tissues that connect so many horizons
you know yeah I mean and I've known Matt
but it's good to have that validated
yeah yeah I think it's really good
totally to have that validated some yeah
yeah and they're so curious you ask
these great questions
Oh totally yeah what's so pertinent it's
so pertinent to everything like that
that I do and I'm about for sure but
it's also kind of like I'm just really
aware of like oh so many things and I'm
standing on and that I'm just I start
from to then be interested in and to
circling and all that stuff I'm talking
to the person that was influential and
was a witness to the tissues of what
made that thing that I'm standing on
right and so there's a quality of my
interest is actually it's like tapping
back into itself into the background of
and I'm learning about it and then we're
having this dialogue around it yeah yes
I like that it's fun for you to yeah
yeah this is great
yeah this is great and of course there's
the other level where I'm just like oh
my god you didn't know about that
like I didn't and so there's there's
another part of it to you where it's not
like it's changing my it's not it's not
like I'm finding out I'm finding out
that you're somebody else it's not that
at all it's actually it it's animating
more of like I've had a number of times
especially when you when you talked
about especially when you talked about
right having the skill board right like
I just watched myself kind of like $0.06
that movie the sixth sense of like mmm
right you know he's dead through the
whole movie
and you don't know it and no one knows
it and they're ready at the end he
realized that at the corner of his eye
that he's dead and then everyone starts
realizing it and then it goes to the
beginning of the movie and Joe's scene
after scene after scene and you realized
he was obvious the whole time but
concealed right like some of that I'm
like oh whoa in this way that I'm sure
I'm gonna be thinking about when we're
done here right and is percolating of
like oh yeah so many different parts of
you um are just more animate or more
meaningful to me or more salient in ways
that make a lot of sense so you seem
even more both mysterious and coherent
and the thing also Weiss also the thing
about like you talking about that moment
the moment when he hugged you the Swami
hugged you and that that was the moment
where your heart went and I'm like cuz
I've seen that in you I've seen that an
experience that with you and I've
watched world be moved when that happens
right and so that's something that I'm
on some level I deeply understand about
you and I'm constantly in some way in
relationship with you as your friend to
that so like to kind of get this sense
of of that and then oh and then make
sense of it there's this her munetaka
her genetic circles that are going on
right
of unfolding meetings that are happening
happening right in this conversation so
I'm glad we're filming it when it'd be
hard no if we didn't record it oh my god
we had this awesome conversation it was
like yes yes I hit the button and I have
done that before believe I'm doing that
pulsing things so this seems like a good
place chronologically to kind of leave
it off right yes that's right with
Warner which is a whole world and let's
just kind of like let the conversation
sink in and like next week or something
like that we can get that God and I'll
be so great and this all started all of
it started with you're like yeah what is
that hotness thing yeah that's a really
good question
right and yeah this is where we are so
far in that right yeah yes awesome day
bye